<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>GetHFData | msperlin</title>
    <link>http://www.msperlin.com/category/gethfdata/</link>
      <atom:link href="http://www.msperlin.com/category/gethfdata/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>GetHFData</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>Marcelo S. Perlin © 2022</copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 08 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>http://www.msperlin.com/img/portrait.jpg</url>
      <title>GetHFData</title>
      <link>http://www.msperlin.com/category/gethfdata/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>B3 is NOT shutting down its ftp site, for now..</title>
      <link>http://www.msperlin.com/post/2019-08-08-ftp-not-shutdown/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://www.msperlin.com/post/2019-08-08-ftp-not-shutdown/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;http://www.msperlin.com/blog/rmarkdown-libs/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Update 2019-08-09: The shutdown is just postponed to 2019-11-14. See the official release &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.b3.com.br/pt_br/noticias/portais-8AE490C86BC98316016BDD1E7BDF14AB.htm?fbclid=IwAR1IY_ILkhkWwsBxFWH4pQEBx-OqxcEDxfmg22Ii5tep_dtzyKw9casag5o&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Surprise, surprise. B3’s ftp site is still up and running.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Following previous &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.msperlin.com/blog/post/2019-07-01-ftp-shutdown/&#34;&gt;post&lt;/a&gt; regarding the shutdown of B3’s ftp site and its impact over GetHFData, I’m happy to report that the site is up and running.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can check it with code:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;library(GetHFData)
library(tidyverse)

df.ftp &amp;lt;- ghfd_get_ftp_contents(type.market = &amp;#39;equity&amp;#39;)

# check time difference
max(df.ftp$dates) - min(df.ftp$dates)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s download some trade data:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;df.trades &amp;lt;- ghfd_get_HF_data(my.assets = &amp;#39;PETR3&amp;#39;, 
                              type.market = &amp;#39;equity&amp;#39;, 
                              first.date = max(df.ftp$dates)-3, 
                              last.date = max(df.ftp$dates),
                              type.data = &amp;#39;trades&amp;#39;, type.output = &amp;#39;agg&amp;#39;, 
                              first.time =  &amp;#39;11:00:00&amp;#39;, last.time = &amp;#39;18:00:00&amp;#39;, dl.dir = tempdir()
                              )&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And check it out:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;glimpse(df.trades)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Its working fine. The amount of data available at the ftp is more than necessary for research and class material.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m not really sure what happened. It could be a simple delay to the shutdown. Lets keep our fingers crossed.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>B3 is shutting down its ftp site</title>
      <link>http://www.msperlin.com/post/2019-07-01-ftp-shutdown/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://www.msperlin.com/post/2019-07-01-ftp-shutdown/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;http://www.msperlin.com/blog/rmarkdown-libs/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Well, bad news travels fast. &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the last couple of weeks I’ve been receiving a couple of emails regarding B3’s &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.b3.com.br/data/files/40/76/60/59/745666102F630666AC094EA8/CE%20018-2019%20-%20Prorroga%C3%A7%C3%A3o%20do%20Prazo%20de%20Desativa%C3%A7%C3%A3o%20do%20Servior%20FTP.pdf&#34;&gt;decision&lt;/a&gt; of shutting down its &lt;a href=&#34;ftp://ftp.bmf.com.br/&#34;&gt;ftp site&lt;/a&gt;. More specifically, users are eager to know how it will impact my data grabbing packages in CRAN. I’ll use this post to explain the situation for everyone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The only package affected directly will be &lt;code&gt;GetHFData&lt;/code&gt;, which uses the ftp site for downloading the raw zipped files with trades and quotes. The main function will no longer work as all internet files are not available. However, the function that reads the local files, &lt;code&gt;GetHFData::ghfd_read_file()&lt;/code&gt;, will still work as long as you have the files available in your computer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Soon I’ll release an update to &lt;code&gt;GetHFData&lt;/code&gt; that will bypass the ftp checking process. Users will be able to load up the code with local files. Btw, before anyone asks, I’m not aware of any other site that distributes the zipped files. In this topic, everyone should know that B3’s web policy does not allow the redistribution of their data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As for my personal opinion on the event, B3 is a private company and can do whatever they want with their data. In fact, it is standard for many international exchanges to sell their high-frequency trade&amp;amp;quote data. However, I fell that they could still offer a free sample of past raw data for students and researchers, keeping &lt;code&gt;GetHFData&lt;/code&gt; alive. I’m not sure how this would hurt their business. In fact, it is easy to argue that the “free” training would help them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the research side, studying microstructure of the Brazilian financial market will become even more difficult now, without easy access to the datasets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a clever stoic man once said, we should only worry about things we can control.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Life (and research) goes on..&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using R to download high frequency trade data diretcly from Bovespa</title>
      <link>http://www.msperlin.com/post/2017-01-02-gethfdata/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://www.msperlin.com/post/2017-01-02-gethfdata/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;Recently, Bovespa, the Brazilian financial exchange company, allowed external access to its &lt;a href=&#34;ftp://ftp.bmf.com.br/&#34;&gt;ftp site&lt;/a&gt;. In this address one can find several information regarding the Brazilian financial system, including datasets with high frequency (tick by tick) trading data for three different markets: equity, options and BMF.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Downloading and processing these files, however, can be exausting. The dataset is composed of zip files with the whole trading data, separated by day and market. These files are huge in size and processing or aggregating them in a usefull manner requires specific knowledge for the structure of the dataset.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The package GetHFData make is easy to access this dataset directly by allowing the easy importation and aggregations of it. Based on this package the user can:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Access the contents of the Bovespa ftp using function function &lt;code&gt;ghfd_get_ftp_contents&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Get the list of available ticker in the trading data using &lt;code&gt;ghfd_get_available_tickers_from_ftp&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Download individual files using &lt;code&gt;ghfd_download_file&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Download and process a batch of dates and assets codes with &lt;code&gt;ghfd_get_HF_data&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More details can be found in my &lt;a href=&#34;https://ssrn.com/abstract=2824058&#34;&gt;SSRN paper&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
