<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Looking Back | msperlin</title>
    <link>https://www.msperlin.com/tag/looking-back/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://www.msperlin.com/tag/looking-back/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Looking Back</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>Marcelo S. Perlin © 2024</copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 29 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://www.msperlin.com/img/portrait.jpg</url>
      <title>Looking Back</title>
      <link>https://www.msperlin.com/tag/looking-back/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Looking back at 2023 and plans for 2024</title>
      <link>https://www.msperlin.com/post/2023-12-29-looking-back-2023/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.msperlin.com/post/2023-12-29-looking-back-2023/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;Another year has passed and now its time to discuss what happened in this cycle, along with future projects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Year 2023 passed by very quickly, and I’m grateful for everything I’ve learned and experienced. Here are the highlights from my work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;highlights-of-2023-and-2022&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Highlights of 2023 and 2022&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;academic-papers&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Academic Papers&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I co-authored a single academic papers during this period:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://periodicos.fgv.br/rbfin/article/view/89040&#34;&gt;What is the sustainable withdraw rate for Brazil?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, many papers are ready (or almost ready) for submission. I expect that 2024 will be a year with many publications.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;books&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Books&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I revised book &lt;a href=&#34;https://msperlin.com/publication/2023_book-afedr-en/&#34;&gt;Analyzing Financial and Economic Data with R&lt;/a&gt; for its second edition. Most of the changes are in the background, with the use of Quarto technology for &lt;a href=&#34;https://quarto.org/docs/books/&#34;&gt;books&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I wrote and published book &lt;a href=&#34;https://msperlin.com/publication/2023_book-qrcp/&#34;&gt;Questões de R em Concursos Públicos&lt;/a&gt;, containing several questions about R used in public examinations in Brazil.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;r-packages&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;R Packages&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nothing special to report here, besides the usual maintainence of current packages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;checking-previous-plans&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Checking previous plans&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the end of 2022, my plans for 2023 &lt;a href=&#34;https://msperlin.com/post/2022-12-29-looking-back-2022/&#34;&gt;were&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;dl&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Publish revision of &lt;em&gt;Analyzing Financial and Economic Data with R&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;
Done! The new edition is published in &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.com/Analyzing-Financial-Economic-Data-R/dp/171062731X&#34;&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Publish revision of &lt;em&gt;Análise de Dados Financeiros e Econômicos com o R&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;
Not done! The revision will be up in early 2024, and probably distributed as two separate books, one as an introduction to R and other as Data Analysis with R.
&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Write and publish paper about research schollarships&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;
The paper is already submitted to a high impact journal. This is a very interesting paper, with impactful results. I hope that soon I’ll be able to write about it in the blog.
&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;plans-for-2024&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Plans for 2024&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;dl&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Publish revision of &lt;em&gt;Análise de Dados Financeiros e Econômicos com o R&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;
My book in R is likely to be separated into two distinct books, one as “An introduction to R”, and other as “Data Analysis with R”.
&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Paper “Using ChatGPT for creating multi-language finance related sentiment dictionaries”&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;
co-authored with Marcos Reichert, this paper is submitted and likelly to be published in 2024.
&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Paper “Risk forecasting comparisons in decentralized finance: An approach in constant product market makers”&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;
co-authored with Lucas Mussoi and Fernanda Muller, this paper is also submitted and likelly to be published in 2024.
&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Looking back at 2021-2022 and plans for 2023</title>
      <link>https://www.msperlin.com/post/2022-12-29-looking-back-2022/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.msperlin.com/post/2022-12-29-looking-back-2022/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;Every end of year I write about what happened during the yearly cycle and what’s to come.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This year was very special and impactful for me. I learned a lot about myself, about what I do and why. Here are the highlights.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;highlights-of-2022-and-2021&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Highlights of 2022 and 2021&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;academic-papers&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Academic Papers&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I published and co-authored several academic papers during this period:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://bibliotecadigital.fgv.br/ojs/index.php/rbfin/article/view/85378&#34;&gt;What drives the release of material facts for Brazilian stocks?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.joi.2022.101287&#34;&gt;The Academic Inbreeding Controversy: Analysis and Evidence from Brazil&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://dx.doi.org/10.1108/GM-06-2019-0088&#34;&gt;Board gender diversity: performance and risk of Brazilian firms&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.15728/bbr.2021.18.5.5&#34;&gt;O Impacto da Titulação Acadêmica de Conselheiros e Diretores sobre a Performance de Empresas Negociadas na B3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;books&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Books&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The first edition of book &lt;a href=&#34;https://msperlin.com/vdr/&#34;&gt;Visualização de Dados com o R&lt;/a&gt; was published in October 2022. This was a great project and I had a great time and learned a lot doing it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The third edition of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.msperlin.com/adfeR/&#34;&gt;Análise de Dados Financeiros e Econômicos com o R&lt;/a&gt; was published.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;r-packages&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;R Packages&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Package &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/ropensci/yfR/&#34;&gt;yfR&lt;/a&gt; is the new iteration of BatchGetSymbols, with several new features and improvements. I had a very good experience submitting it for publication in &lt;a href=&#34;https://ropensci.org/&#34;&gt;ropensci&lt;/a&gt;. Both reviewers had great ideas that were implemented.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;checking-previous-plans&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Checking previous plans&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the end of 2020, my plans for 2021 and 2021 &lt;a href=&#34;https://msperlin.com/post/2020-12-22-looking-back-2020/&#34;&gt;were&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;dl&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Publish new R/ggplot2 book (&lt;em&gt;Visualização de Dados com R&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;
Done! :)
&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Publish third edition of &lt;em&gt;Análise de Dados Financeiros e Econômicos com o R&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;
Also done! :)
&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Publish board papers&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;
Done! See it &lt;a href=&#34;https://msperlin.com/publication/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Publish paper about academic inbreeding&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;
Done! The paper is available at &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.joi.2022.101287&#34;&gt;JOI&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;plans-for-2023&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Plans for 2023&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;dl&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Publish revision of &lt;em&gt;Analyzing Financial and Economic Data with R&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;
I’m currently working on it. I’m implementing major changes in the background, on how the book is written and compiled. On a side note, it is great to have time to think about compiling books using Rmarkdown, and organizing it in a common framework. This will make it easier to update ALL books over time.
&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Publish revision of &lt;em&gt;Análise de Dados Financeiros e Econômicos com o R&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;
Same as previous revision. Almost everything improved in the english version will also be done here.
&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Write and publish paper about research schollarships&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;
This is is WIP (work in progress). I have no idea how it will turn out, but the main guideline is investigating the effects (or causes) of research schollarships (&lt;em&gt;Bolsas de Produtividade&lt;/em&gt;) in Brazil. Final version and publication is likelly to happen in 2024.
&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Looking back at 2020 and plans for 2021</title>
      <link>https://www.msperlin.com/post/2020-12-22-looking-back-2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.msperlin.com/post/2020-12-22-looking-back-2020/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;https://www.msperlin.com/rmarkdown-libs/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Wow, what a &lt;strong&gt;long&lt;/strong&gt; year! The pandemic affected everyone, changing the way we live and relate to one another. This was a year full of lessons and we must be thankful and be able to appreciate life even more. Events such as these show how little our “problems” are when put into perspective.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m lucky that, despite the lockdown, I was able to work from home this year. Lets have a look at the highlights.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;highlights-of-2020&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Highlights of 2020&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;academic-papers&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Academic Papers&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This year I published and co-authored two academic papers:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://rac.anpad.org.br/index.php/rac/article/view/1420&#34;&gt;A Garch Tutorial in R - RAC&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://linkinghub.elsevier.com/retrieve/pii/S1062940820301406&#34;&gt;Does algorithmic trading harm liquidity? Evidence from Brazil - NAJEF&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also worked towards my paper pipeline in corporate finance, with the following papers, which are currently under review:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Financial Performance and Academic Titles of Advisers and Directors of Brazilian Companies&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Boards and Gender for Brazilian Listed Companies&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Description of Boards in Brazil&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;books&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Books&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second edition of my R book - &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.msperlin.com/publication/2020_book-afedr-en/&#34;&gt;Analyzing Financial and Economic Data with R&lt;/a&gt; was published in January 2020. I spend most of 2019 working towards this edition and I’m very pleased with the result. The book improved a lot, with a more polished content.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m also happy to report that my two other books, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.com.br/dp/B07DN4M357&#34;&gt;padfR&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.amazon.com.br/dp/B07RR9K9PV&#34;&gt;pirf&lt;/a&gt;, are receiving great reviews in Amazon.com.br. This is great news, motivating the future editions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;r-packages&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;R Packages&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This year I “broke” package &lt;code&gt;GetDFPData&lt;/code&gt; into two: &lt;code&gt;GetDFPData2&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;GetFREData&lt;/code&gt;. Both are still in &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/msperlin&#34;&gt;Github&lt;/a&gt; but I’ll soon release it to CRAN. You can read more about this decision &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.msperlin.com/post/2020-07-18-new_packages-getfredata-getdfpdata2/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Additionally, I also wrote the book package &lt;code&gt;afedR&lt;/code&gt;, which facilitates the reproducibility of all book examples. See more details about it &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.msperlin.com/post/2020-02-25-afedr-ed2-slides-available/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;checking-2019s-plans&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Checking 2019’s plans&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the end of 2019, my plans for 2020 &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.msperlin.com/post/2019-12-15-looking-back-2019/&#34;&gt;were&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;dl&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Publish afedR (analyzing financial and economic data with R)&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.msperlin.com/post/2020-01-15-afedr-ed2-announcement/&#34;&gt;Done! :)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Finish board papers&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Almost Done. All papers are now in review and, hopefully, are going to be published soon.
&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Start “personal finance project”&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Not done. This is an idea that I’m struggling with. I’m not really sure how to implement it and still have to figure out the details.
&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;plans-for-2021&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Plans for 2021&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;dl&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Publish new R/ggplot2 book (&lt;em&gt;Visualização de Dados com R&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;This book will be mostly about using &lt;code&gt;ggplot2&lt;/code&gt; in data visualization. It will be written in portuguese and, if it comes out right and do well, I’ll translate into english. I already got 2 chapters written, but still missing a lot of work and content.
&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Publish third edition of &lt;em&gt;Análise de Dados Financeiros e Econômicos com o R&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;The portuguese version of my R book is already in its third edition and I’m very excited for this new edition. It will incorporate many changes from the english edition and more!
&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Publish board papers&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;Soon. The three papers are in revision.
&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Publish paper about academic inbreeding&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;I’m writing a new paper about the effects of academic inbreeding in Brazil using Lattes data. The paper is its final internal review and will soon be sent to for its formal review. The results are very interesting and I hope to write more about it soon.
&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
